Baris Kasikci

Assistant Professor Electrical Engineering and Computer Science University of Michigan

 $4820~\mathrm{BBB}$ 2260 Hayward Street Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA +1 (734) 763-1560 barisk@umich.edu

http://web.eecs.umich.edu/~barisk

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is centered around developing techniques, tools, and environments that help developers build more reliable, secure, and efficient software. I am interested in developing techniques and building systems that allow programmers to better reason about their code. I am also interested in system support for emerging hardware platforms, efficient runtime instrumentation, hardware and runtime support for enhancing system security, and program analysis.

EDUCATION

Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Sep. 2010–Dec. 2015

Thesis: Techniques for Detection, Root Cause Diagnosis,

and Classification of In-Production Concurrency Bugs

Advisor: Prof. George Candea

Middle East Technical University (METU)

Ankara, Turkey

Sep. 2002-Jun. 2006

M.Sc. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Sep. 2006-Jun. 2009

Thesis: Variability Modeling in Software Product Lines

Graduated with the top grade Advisor: Prof. Semih Bilgen

B.Sc. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Project: Embedded Target Estimation, Detection, and Tracking

Graduated with High Honors Advisor: Prof. Arzu Koc

AWARDS AND HONORS

Jay Lepreau Best Paper Award, OSDI	2018
Outstanding Reviewer Award, WWW	2017
Patrick Denantes Memorial Prize for outstanding PhD thesis, EPFL	2016
EuroSys Roger Needham Award for Best PhD. Thesis in Computer Systems in Europe	2016
Intel Corp. Software and Services Group, Grant	2014 – 2016
VMware Inc., Doctoral Fellowship	2014 – 2015
EPFL, Doctoral Fellowship	2010-2011
Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey, Master Scholarship	2006-2008
Middle East Technical University, Dean's High Honor List	2006
Middle East Technical University,	
Award for Best Team Performance, Undergraduate Final Project	2006
Turkish Customs Association, Scholarship	2002 - 2006

Funding

Intel Faculty Award, Automated Performance Optimization, 75K USD, PI 2018
Intel Gift, SysTEX'18 Workshop Sponsorship, 2K USD, PI 2018
Michigan Cambridge Research Initiative, 15K USD, PI 2018
Applications Driving Architectures, 1,245M USD, PI 2018

Intel Faculty Award, Performance Debugging, 75K USD, PI 2017

EMPLOYMENT

Research on computer systems and networks

University of Michigan
Assistant Professor
Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department

Microsoft Research
Researcher

Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA
Sep. 2017–present

Cambridge, United Kingdom
Aug. 2016–Aug. 2017

Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Postdoctoral Researcher Research on software security Lausanne, Switzerland

Dec. 2015-Jul. 2016

• I developed infrastructure that relies on hardware support to improve software security.

Research Assistant Sep. 2010–Dec. 2015

Research on software reliability with an emphasis on concurrent software

- I developed **Gist**, the first technique for accurately, efficiently, and automatically diagnosing the root causes of in-production failures, by using a combination of static and dynamic program analysis.
- I developed RaceMob, the first automated in-production data race detection technique that can be kept always-on and provides high accuracy, by combining static data race detection with adaptive, crowdsourced dynamic data race detection.
- I developed **Portend**, a high-accuracy technique to classify data races according to their potential consequences under arbitrary memory models, by using symbolic program analysis to explore multiple program paths and schedules to determine the effects of data races.
- I developed Bias-Free Sampling, a technique that allows efficient sampling of rarely executed code (where bugs often lurk) without over-sampling frequently executed code, by using a new sampling algorithm and existing hardware support.

Intel Corp. Santa Clara, CA, USA Research Intern Jul. 2015-Sep. 2015

Automated root cause diagnosis of failures and security enhancements using hardware support

- I developed a tool that allows developers to determine which program statements operate on a given data type at runtime using a mix of static program analysis and hardware support. In our experiments, this tool reduces the number of statements to examine during debugging by an order of magnitude. This tool is being extended internally at Intel.
- I began investigating hardware support for enhancing system security, in particular, efficient path profiling for auditing and detecting control flow hijack attacks.

VMware Inc. Palo Alto, CA, USA

Research and Development Intern

Automated debugging and runtime control flow tracking

Jun. 2014-Sep. 2014

- I implemented a runtime for efficient control flow tracking in software. This work formed the basis of my **Gist** work on root cause diagnosis.
- I designed and implemented an infrastructure to remotely debug and profile VMware VCenter virtual machine management software, while it is running in production. This infrastructure is used by VCenter developers at VMWare.

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA, USA Research Intern Jun. 2013-Sep. 2013

Efficient runtime execution sampling technique and low overhead coverage measurement

- I worked on the design of the Bias-Free Sampling framework for efficient runtime sampling. I designed and implemented the bias-free sampling framework for managed code (i.e., C#). This tool is internally used at Microsoft.
- I designed and implemented a fault injection tool to detect resource leakage problems using dynamic binary instrumentation.

Siemens Corporate Technology

Senior Software Engineer

Embedded home and industrial automation software

Istanbul, Turkey Mar. 2008–May 2010

• I designed and implemented a real-time embedded gateway software between Siemens communication processors and a building automation system using C++ on top of VxWorks.

Aselsan Electronic Industries

Ankara, Turkey

Software Engineer

May 2006-Mar. 2008

Embedded motor control and functional testing infrastructure

• I was responsible for a real-time embedded control software for turret motor control. I also designed and implemented a full-system functional testing software using C++ on top of VxWorks for Power PC architectures.

Student Intern

Jun. 2005–Jul. 2005

Embedded software development

• I developed embedded control software for a night vision camera using C++ and PIC assembly on a PIC microcontroller.

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Morpheus: A Vulnerability-Tolerant Secure Architecture Based on Ensembles of Moving Target Defenses with Churn. Mark Gallagher, Lauren Biernacki, Shibo Chen, Zelalem Birhanu Aweke, Salessawi Ferede Yitbarek, Misiker Tadesse Aga, Austin Harris, Zhixing Xu, Baris Kasikci, Valeria Bertacco, Sharad Malik, Mohit Tiwari, and Todd Austin. *Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)*, Providence, RI, March 2019.
- [2] REPT: Reverse Debugging of Failures in Deployed Software. Xinyang Ge Weidong Cui, Baris Kasikci, Ben Niu, Upamanyu Sharma, Ruoyu Wang, and Insu Yun. *OSDI*, Carlsbad, USA, October 2018.
- [3] Foreshadow: Extracting the Keys to the Intel SGX Kingdom with Transient Out-of-Order Execution. Jo Van Bulck, Marina Minkin, Ofir Weisse, Daniel Genkin, Baris Kasikci, Frank Piessens, Mark Silberstein, Thomas F. Wenisch, Yuval Yarom, and Raoul Strackx. USENIX Security, Baltimore, USA, August 2018.
- [4] Cntr: Lightweight OS Containers. Jorg Thalheim, Pramod Bhatotia, Pedro Fonseca, and Baris Kasikci. *USENIX ATC*, Boston, USA, July 2018.
- [5] Foreshadow-NG: Breaking the Virtual Memory Abstraction with Transient Out-of-Order Execution. Ofir Weisse, Jo Van Bulck, Marina Minkin, Daniel Genkin, Baris Kasikci, Frank Piessens, Mark Silberstein, Raoul Strackx, Thomas F. Wenisch, and Yuval Yarom. Technical report, 2018.
- [6] Lazy Diagnosis of In-Production Concurrency Bugs. Baris Kasikci, Weidong Cui, Xinyang Ge, and Ben Niu. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Shanghai, China, October 2017.
- [7] Failure Sketching: A Technique for Automated Root Cause Diagnosis of In-Production Failures. Baris Kasikci, Benjamin Schubert, Cristiano Pereira, Gilles Pokam, and George Candea. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Monterey, CA, October 2015.
- [8] Failure Sketches: A Better Way to Debug. Baris Kasikci, Benjamin Schubert, Cristiano Pereira, Gilles Pokam, Madanlal Musuvathi, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems, Kartause Ittingen, Switzerland, May 2015.
- [9] Automated Classification of Data Races Under Both Strong and Weak Memory Models. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. ACM Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems (TOPLAS), May 2015.

- [10] Efficient Tracing of Cold Code Via Bias-Free Sampling. Baris Kasikci, Thomas Ball, George Candea, John Erickson, and Madanlal Musuvathi. *USENIX ATC*, Philadelphia, PA, June 2014.
- [11] Lockout: Efficient Testing for Deadlock Bugs. Ali Kheradmand, Baris Kasikci, and George Candea. 5th Workshop on Determinism and Correctness in Parallel Programming (WoDet), Salt Lake City, UT, March 2014.
- [12] RaceMob: Crowdsourced Data Race Detection. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Farmington, PA, November 2013.
- [13] Automated Debugging for Arbitrarily Long Executions. Cristian Zamfir, Baris Kasikci, Johannes Kinder, Edouard Bugnion, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems, Santa Ana Pueblo, NM, May 2013.
- [14] CORD: A Collaborative Framework for Distributed Data Race Detection. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Dependable Systems (HotDep), Hollywood, CA, October 2012.
- [15] Data Races vs. Data Race Bugs: Telling the Difference with Portend. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. *Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)*, London, UK, March 2012.
- [16] Scalable Modeling of Software Product Line Variability. Baris Kasikci and Semih Bilgen. Workshop on Scalable Modeling Techniques for Software Product Lines (SCALE), San Francisco, CA, August 2009.

TALKS

July 2018
May 2018
May 2018
Apr. 2017
Jul. 2016
Apr. 2016
Apr. 2016
Apr. 2016
Mar. 2016
Feb. 2016
Feb. 2016
Feb. 2016

• Boston University, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• Georgia Institute of Technology, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• VMWare Research, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• University of British Columbia, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• Simon Fraser University, Seminar	Jan.	2016
Automated Root Cause Diagnosis of In-Production Failures		
• Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP)	Oct.	2015
• Intel Corp.	Sep.	2015
• Google	Sep.	2015
• VMware Inc.	Sep.	2015
Failure Sketches: A Better Way to Debug	_	
• EcoCloud Annual Event		2015
• Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS) Efficient Tracing of Cold Code via Bias-Free Sampling	May	2015
USENIX Annual Technical Conference (USENIX ATC)	Jun.	2014
Lockout: Efficient Testing for Deadlock Bugs	9 0	
• Workshop on Determinism and Correctness in Parallel Programming (WoDet)	Mar.	2014
RaceMob: Crowdsourced Data Race Detection. • Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP)	Oct	2013
• EPFL Systems Seminar		2013
CoRD: A Collaborative Framework for Distributed Data Race Detection	Oct.	2013
• Workshop on Hot Topics in System Dependability (HotDep)	Oct.	2012
Data Races vs. Data Race Bugs: Telling the Difference with Portend		
• International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)	Mar	2012
How to Build Reliable Software?	mai.	2012
• Seminar talk to the incoming undergraduate students at EPFL	Sep.	2011
Professional Service		
PC Chair Workshop on System Software for Trusted Evention (SysTEV) (so leasted with CCS/18)		2010
Workshop on System Software for Trusted Execution (SysTEX) (co-located with CCS'18) Symposium on Cloud Computing (SoCC) Poster Session		2018 2018
DC M 1		
PC Member Symposium on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP)		2019
EuroSys		2019
International Conference on Virtual Execution Environments (VEE)		2019
International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS)		2019
EuroSys Roger Needham PhD Award Committee 2019 EuroSys Doctoral Workshop (EuroD	W)	2019 2018
Symposium on Cloud Computing (SoCC) International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS)		2017
World Wide Web Conference (WWW)		2017
International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA), Artifact Evaluation Com	mittee	2014
Journal Reviewer		
Transactions on Architecture and Code Optimization		2018
Transactions on Software Engineering		2015
Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology		2015

Extended Review Committee

Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS) 2018

Shadow PC Member

EuroSys Conference on Computer Systems	(EuroSys)	2013, 2015

External Reviewer

Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP)	2011. 2013
EuroSys Conf. on Computer Systems (EuroSys)	2011, 2012
USENIX Annual Technical Conf. (USENIX ATC)	2011
Intl. Conf. on Compiler Construction (CC)	2017
Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS)	2011, 2013
Conf. on Innovative Data Systems Research (CIDR)	2013
Intl. Conf. on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN)	2011, 2013
Symposium on Cloud Computing (SOCC)	2012
Intl. SPIN Workshop on Model Checking of Software (SPIN)	2011

Committee Member

EPFL Doctoral School of	Computer and	Communication Sciences Audit	Committee 2	2015
-------------------------	--------------	------------------------------	-------------	------

TEACHING

Introduction to Operating Systems (EECS 482) (undergrad level, University of Michigan) 2018, 2019 Advanced Topics in Operating Systems (EECS 582) (grad level, University of Michigan) 2017, 2019

RESEARCH MENTORING

PhD	
Tanvir Ahmed Khan	Jan 2018–
Kevin Loughlin	Sep 2018–
Andrew Loveless	Sep 2018–
Jiacheng Ma	Sep 2018–
Ian Neal	Sep 2018–
Ofir Weisse	Sep 2017–
Gefei Zuo	Sep 2018–
Master's John Wu	Sep 2018–
Undergraduate	
Yifan Dai	May 2018–
Liran Xiao	May 2018–
Yifan Zhao	May 2018–
Yimeng Zhou	May 2018–
8 8	111ay 2010

Languages

English: fluent French: fluent Turkish: native German: beginner

References

Available upon request